{
  "reference_number": "11972",
  "clauses": [
    {
      "question": "1. What process should the Government use to set a new emissions reduction target in legislation?",
      "question_index": 0,
      "answer": "The Government sets a 2050 target in legislation now",
      "answer_index": 0,
      "notes": null
    },
    {
      "question": "2. If the Government sets a 2050 target now, which is the best target for New Zealand?",
      "question_index": 1,
      "answer": "Net Zero Emissions - Net zero emissions across all greenhouse gases by 2050",
      "answer_index": 1,
      "notes": null
    },
    {
      "question": "3. How should New Zealand meet its targets?",
      "question_index": 2,
      "answer": "Domestic emissions reductions only (including from new forest planting)",
      "answer_index": 7,
      "notes": "New Zealand is best placed to reduce its emissions by itself without having to buy overseas credits. In terms of future sustainability,\n\n and also the health of the people of New Zealand, reducing our emissions through forestry, swapping agriculture for horticulture, and\n using electric vehicles would be much better."
    },
    {
      "question": "4. Should the Zero Carbon Bill allow the 2050 target to be revised if circumstances change?",
      "question_index": 3,
      "answer": "Yes",
      "answer_index": 3,
      "notes": "It should allow the target to be revised to be zero carbon earlier. 2050 is too late. We are already seeing the serious effects of climate\n change now. Ideally the target should be for 2030. New Zealand needs to lead the way in this area, and be a role model to other\n\n countries. New Zealand cannot afford to lag in this area and wait for bigger countries to make a move. However, the Bill should not\n allow the target to be revised to allow us to reach zero carbon later."
    },
    {
      "question": "5. The Government proposes that three emissions budgets of five years each (i.e. covering the next 15 years) be in place at any given time. Do you agree with this proposal?",
      "question_index": 15,
      "answer": "Yes",
      "answer_index": 3,
      "notes": null
    },
    {
      "question": "6. Should the Government be able to alter the last emissions budget (i.e. furthest into the future)?",
      "question_index": 4,
      "answer": "No - emissions budgets should not be able to be changed",
      "answer_index": 9,
      "notes": "if governments can change the emissions budget then they might be able to allow New Zealand to not reduce its carbon emissions\n\n as fast as needed. We have seen previous governments do this, so I don't think they should be able to be changed to allow more\n leeway for governments."
    },
    {
      "question": "7. Should the Government have the ability to review and adjust the second emissions budget within a specific range under exceptional circumstances? See p36 Our Climate Your Say",
      "question_index": 5,
      "answer": "No",
      "answer_index": 8,
      "notes": "Governments keep changing their emissions budgets, and New Zealand failed its obligations under the Kyoto Protocol, so in my view,\nthey should not be able to review it and change it. Following a natural disaster or other exceptional circumstances, climate change\n\npolicy should not be the first thing to get changed to protect our economic position. Instead we should borrow more money. New\nZealand is a growing country, and we will be able to pay back the money in the future. If we do ensure that our targets are met, even\n\nunder exceptional circumstances, then we will be better placed to provide a home to people to ensure our government keeps\ngrowing and working."
    },
    {
      "question": "8. Do you agree with the considerations we propose that the Government and the Climate Change Commission take into account when advising on and setting budgets? See p44 Our Climate Your Say",
      "question_index": 6,
      "answer": "Yes",
      "answer_index": 3,
      "notes": "It is important to consider the socio-economic health of people who will be affected. This means the government needs to act quickly\nto begin to transition high carbon industries to something else. However I am concerned about the commissions three government\n\nobjectives \"sustainable economy, global and local leadership, and creating a just and inclusive society.\" I think it is very important to\ncreate these, but the overall government objective should be working towards lowering our emissions. And these three objectives\n\nshould be the result of lowering our emissions. It is really important that the climate change commissioners have the scientific\nknowledge that our economy cannot be sustainable if we continue to emit at the rate that we are, or even if we reduce it slightly. It is\n\nvery important that the climate change commissioners are faced with the reality of the effects of climate change so that they create\npolicy that takes that into account. I do think that the objectives of creating global and local leadership are great, and creating a just\nand inclusive society. The objective of creating a sustainable economy is good as long as the commissioners have a strong scientific\n\nunderstanding to inform their decisions."
    },
    {
      "question": "9. Should the Zero Carbon Bill require Governments to set out plans within a certain timeframe to achieve the emissions budgets?",
      "question_index": 7,
      "answer": "Yes",
      "answer_index": 3,
      "notes": "This is very important. Governments have short term thinking because of the nature of our short electoral cycle, and so we need to\n\nset clear targets that governments cannot leave to the next government to sort out (which they inevitably will not because something\nmore immediately pressing will come up)."
    },
    {
      "question": "10. What are the most important issues for the Government to consider in setting plans to meet budgets? For example, who do we need to work with, what else needs to be considered?",
      "question_index": 8,
      "answer": null,
      "answer_index": 5,
      "notes": "Low income groups - studies show that low income families that work closely with the land, and especially indigenous people are\n\nmore likely to be affected by climate change. The government needs to ensure that they are protecting our climate for our most\nvulnerable people, and for those who rely on the land. The government needs to ensure that it makes these targets with iwi and\n\nhapu to ensure they are consistent with tikanga Maori."
    },
    {
      "question": "11. The Government has proposed that the Climate Change Commission advises on and monitors New Zealand's progress towards its goals. Do you agree with these functions? See p42 Our Climate Your Say",
      "question_index": 9,
      "answer": "Yes",
      "answer_index": 3,
      "notes": "But also I think they should have decision making power. This means that the Climate Change Commission will have much better\nability to ensure that we do actually stick to our targets. While no other country has done this, this would be New Zealand trail blazing\nthe way. We really need to ensure that there are people who have strong power who can act to ensure our environment and climate\n\nis protected, despite other political issues. We rely on our environment for everything, and if we do not have a stable climate\neverything else will be destabilised too."
    },
    {
      "question": "12. What role do you think the Climate Change Commission should have in relation to the New Zealand Emissions Trading Scheme (NZ ETS)?",
      "question_index": 10,
      "answer": "Makes decisions itself in respect of the number of units available in the NZ ETS",
      "answer_index": 10,
      "notes": "Its independence will ensure that the Climate Change Commission does what is best for the New Zealand environment, regardless of\n\nour economic situation. We must prioritise our climate before the economy if we want to continue living on this Earth."
    },
    {
      "question": "13. The Government has proposed that Climate Change Commissioners need to have a range of essential and desirable expertise. Do you agree with the proposed expertise? See p45 Our Climate Your Say",
      "question_index": 11,
      "answer": "Yes",
      "answer_index": 3,
      "notes": "It's also really important that the climate change commissioners have an understanding of tikanga Maori, and include experts in\n\ntikanga and Te Ao Maori, to ensure that we incorporate matauranga Maori into the expertise."
    },
    {
      "question": "14. Do you think the Zero Carbon Bill should cover adapting to climate change?",
      "question_index": 12,
      "answer": "Yes",
      "answer_index": 3,
      "notes": "We are already facing the effects of climate change. This bill is so important to slow the progression of climate change, but we still\n\nneed to ensure that we are adapting to the new climate as well."
    },
    {
      "question": "15. The Government has proposed a number of new functions to help us adapt to climate change. Do you agree with the proposed functions? See p47 Our Climate Your Say",
      "question_index": 13,
      "answer": "Yes",
      "answer_index": 3,
      "notes": "Yes these provisions will be really important in the coming years, and ensure we are prepared for the changes to our climate."
    },
    {
      "question": "16. Should we explore setting up a targeted adaptation reporting power that could see some organisations share information on their exposure to climate change risks?",
      "question_index": 14,
      "answer": "Yes",
      "answer_index": 3,
      "notes": null
    },
    {
      "question": "Do you have any other comments you'd like to make?",
      "question_index": 16,
      "answer": null,
      "answer_index": 5,
      "notes": "I worry about climate change every single day and have for as long as I can remember (I am 24). Most days I get sad for climate\n\nchange related reasons - the winter is not as cold as it should be, increased forest fires, more severe storms, etc. It really scares me\nbecause I don't know what will happen to the world. New Zealand has a great climate, but with climate change increasing it looks like\n\nmost of the world will become difficult to live in. New Zealand needs to be able to feed and house more people, and also make sure\nthat it takes care of its forests and oceans so that they can absorb carbon. It is really heartening to see an action like this because it\n\nmakes me hopeful that we can slow the progression of climate change.\n\n\n\n You have elected to withhold your personal details from publication."
    }
  ]
}
